Bill Sanders Cartoons
Bill Sanders Cartoons
1963-1967.
Sanders, Bill.
2 linear ft.
133 original editorial cartoons most of which were published in the Kansas City Star.
2649914
Biographical History
Bill Sanders (1930- ) is an American editorial cartoonist.
Bill Sanders was born in 1930 in Springfield, Tennessee. While attending Western Kentucky University (then Western Kentucky State College), he set a NCAA football record as a quarterback. He also received a B.A. in English while minoring in art under the direction of a watercolor artist. Sanders was pursued by the Cleveland Browns but Sanders was drafted from the Army ROTC into the Army where he was a lieutenant in the Korean War and also in Japan. While in the military he contributed to the Pacific version of Stars and Stripes.
Following the war, Sanders sought a position at the Greensboro Daily News and became a sports writer-cartoonist for the paper in 1959. Sanders also started his own syndicate and while working for the Daily News, his cartoons were reprinted in several papers in North Carolina, Georgia and Japan. Having grown up and worked in the South, Sanders had been influenced by civil rights issues and his liberal treatment of civil rights issues prompted heated debates about his cartoons.
In 1963, Sanders moved to the Kansas City Star and in 1967 he became the editorial cartoonist at the Milwaukee Journal Sentinel which he retired from in 1991. During this time, Sanders’ work was also syndicated by the King Features Syndicate and appeared in over 200 publications.
Sanders received several awards including Kansas City Civil Liberties Achievement Award, the International Salon of Cartoons Award, the National Headliners Award (1975) and the Wisconsin Civil Liberties Special Award. In 2002, Western Kentucky University formally exhibited his work at a show titled "Bill "Whitey" Sanders: Comic Opera". His cartoons have appeared in the collection: Getting Angry Six Times a Week: a Portfolio of Political Cartoons: 14 major cartoonists and he has published books of entirely his own cartoons: Run for the oval room: they can't corner us there (1974) and Adventures in Whopperland: a collection of political cartoons, written opinions and essays (2006).
In retirement, Sanders continues to submit cartoons to his local paper, the Fort Myers New Press, and publishes them online along with some of his writings through his blog.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bill Sanders Cartoons are arranged into 3 series reflecting the newspaper for which Sanders produced them. The collection consists of 133 original editorial cartoons published during the 1960s. The bulk of the cartoons appeared in the Kansas City Star while three cartoons in the collection are from his earlier work at the Greensboro Daily News and 2 cartoons lack indication of a specific publication. The majority of the cartoons are undated. The folders of dated cartoons typically include a clipping of the cartoon from the newspaper on the back of the original which is stamped with the date.
The cartoons were drawn in ink and crayon on illustration board with screening. The cartoons vary in size.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons are arranged in rough chronological order with three items of Sanders' work for the Greensboro Daily News appearing first followed by his work from the Kansas City Star. Dated cartoons appear first, followed by undated cartoons arranged alphabetically by caption.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Sanders, Bill.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Greensboro Daily News.; Kansas City star (Kansas City, Mo.: 1885); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Missouri.; Cartoonists -- North Carolina.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- Missouri.; Editorial cartoons -- North Carolina.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bill Sanders, 1968 and 1970.
Inventory
See below for an index to the cartoons.
- Cartoons- Greensboro Daily News
  - 26 Feb 1963; undated, 3 items (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
- Cartoons- Kansas City Star
  - Dated, 13 items (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    1963- Aug 14
    1963- Aug 26
    1963- Aug 24
    1963- Aug 27
    1963- Jul 24
    1963- Sep 16
    1964- Feb 18
    1964- Mar 10
    1964- Mar 20
    1964- Mar 24
    1964- Mar 25
    1964- Aug 16
    1964- Sep 28
  - Undated
    - A-B, circa 1963-1967; 9 items (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    - C, circa 1963-1967; 8 items (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
    - D-G, circa 1963-1967; 12 items (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
    - H, circa 1963-1967; 10 items (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - I, circa 1963-1967; 18 items (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
    - K-M, circa 1963-1967; 9 items (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
    - N-P, circa 1963-1967; 10 items (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
    - S-T, circa 1963-1967; 13 items (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
    - V-W, circa 1963-1967; 16 items (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
    - Y, circa 1963-1967; 6 items (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
    - uncaptioned, circa 1963-1967; 4 items (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
- Cartoons- unknown publication
  - uncaptioned, circa 1963-1967; 2 items (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Ackley, Gardner B1F5
Africa B2F3
aliens B1F7
aluminum industry B1F3 B2F2
American Indians B2F5
Asia B1F5
automobile accidents B1F2
biogtry B2F1
Black Power B2F3-B2F4 B2F6
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F3 B1F6 B2F5
Britain B1F7 B2F4
Buddhists B2F1
Bundy, McGeorge B1F3
Burch, Dean B1F4
Castro, Fidel B1F3 B2F3
Central Intelligence Agency B2F2
China B1F3 B1F5-B1F6
civil liberties B1F2
civil rights B1F2 B1F4 B1F6-B2F1 B2F3
communism B1F6 B2F1-B2F2
Congo B1F3 B2F7
Congress B1F1-B2F6
Connally, John B2F7
consumers B1F5
crime B1F7
Cuba B1F6
de Gaulle, Charles B1F2 B2F5
democracy B1F2
Democratic Party B1F2
demonstrations B2F1
diplomacy B2F1
Dirksen, Everett B2F2-B2F3
diseases B2F4
Dixiecrats B1F5
Dominican Republic B2F3
draft B1F5-B1F6
economy B2F1-B2F2
Egypt B1F6-B1F7
elections B1F2 B1F5 B2F4 B2F7
electricity needs B2F4
ethics B1F3 B2F2
Europe B1F7
EXPO 67 B2F5
Fanfani, Amintore B2F4
farming B1F1-B1F2 B1F7
fashion B2F2
Ford, Gerald R. B2F3
foreign aid bill B1F2 B1F4 B2F3
foreign policy B1F7 B2F6
Fowler, Henry H. B1F7
France B2F3
free enterprise B1F7
Fulbright, J. William B2F2 B2F6
Germany B2F3
Ghana B1F6
Goldberg, Arthur B1F3
Goldwater, Barry B1F2 B1F4
Greece B1F5 B2F6
Halleck, Charles B2F3
Harriman, W. Averell B1F3
Helms, Richard B2F2
Ho Chi Minh B1F5 B2F1
Hoover, Hebert B2F2
HUAAC B2F4
Humphrey, Hubert B1F3
ignorance B2F4
immigration B2F5
India B1F5
Indonesia B1F5-B1F6
inflation B1F4-B1F6 B2F2 B2F4
Internal Revenue Service B1F4
Johnson, Lady Bird B1F6
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F2-B1F3 B1F5-B2F4 B2F6
juvenile legal rights B1F4
Kennedy, John F. B1F1-B1F2 B1F4 B1F7 B2F3
Kennedy, Robert F. B1F3 B1F7
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F2 B1F7-B2F1 B2F7
Ku Klux Klan B2F4
labor B2F4
labor laws B2F4
Latin America B2F3
Lindsay, John B2F3
Makarios III B1F5
Malaysia B1F6
McNamara, Robert B1F7 B2F2-B2F3
Middle East B1F5 B2F1 B2F4
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B1F6 B2F3
National Rifle Association B2F1 B2F4
NATO B2F3
nature conservation B2F4
New York City B1F4
nuclear weapons B2F1
Pakistan B1F5
peace B1F5 B1F7 B2F2 B2F4
Percy, Charles H. B1F7
pollution B1F6
poverty B2F4
Powell, Adam Clayton B1F3 B2F1 B2F4-B2F6
prejudice B2F4-B2F5
prices B1F5
Republican Party B1F2 B1F4-B1F5 B1F7 B2F3
Rhodesia B2F2
Rockefeller, Nelson B1F2 B1F7
Romney, George W. B1F7
Russia B1F7
segregation B1F4 B2F2
Smith, Ian B2F3
Soviet Union B1F2 B2F2
space exploration B1F1 B1F7 B2F4
sports B1F6
Stalin, Svetlana B1F6
steel industry B1F4 B1F7-B2F2
strikes B1F7-B2F2
Sukarno B1F3 B1F6 B2F4
Supreme Court B1F4 B2F3
Taft-Hartley Act B2F4
taxes B1F1-B1F2 B1F4 B2F2
television B1F6
transit B1F4
Tshombe, Moise B2F7
Turkey B1F7 B2F6
U.S. Mail B1F6
unions B1F1 B1F4 B1F6
United Nations B1F5 B2F7
Vietnam War B1F2-B1F3 B1F5 B1F7-B2F5
voting rights B2F2
Walker, Edwin B2F7
Yarborough, Don B2F7
Zedong, Mao B1F2-B1F3 B1F5-B1F6 B2F1-B2F2 B2F4